# Ranjeet Singh

I'm a passionate and hands-on data scientist with both industrial and academic research experience in Machine learning and Deep learning. I'm especially fascinated about deep learning inspired computer vision but I'm also keen to dive into classical Computer Vision. My experience involves applications of Deep learning to Speech Recognition and Computer Vision both. With these skills, I have assisted my organisations in improving the user experience of their products and services.

### in (7)

**Data Scientist** at Roadzen, New Delhi, India □ +919041362736

### Skills

Python, Tensorflow, Keras, OpenCV

Docker, BigQuery, GCP, SQL, MySQL

HTML, CSS, Javascript

# Experience

Roadzen, New Delhi

Data Scientist, Oct 2018 till now

Working classical and deep learning based computer vision with application to insurance Primarily focused on building artificial intelligence systems for automating claim process, detecting damages and frauds

#### Quantiphi Inc., Mumbai

Machine Learning Engineer, Feb 2018 - Sept 2018

Worked on state of the art Language Modelling techniques for Speech Recognition for Trading domain

### Jugnoo, Chandigarh

Data Scientist, Jan 2017- Feb 2018

Built data driven intelligent applications for Jugnoo's various verticals

### **Education**

Bachelor of Technology, 2016 - Major in Electronics Minor in Computer science Lovely Professional University

## Master of Technology, Dropout - Digital Signal Processing

Lovely Professional University

Thesis - Demographics estimation using Deep learning

Thesis overview - This work tackles the problems of demographics estimation from image and video with potential application in targeted advertising.

### Research

MIDAS Lab, IIIT Delhi - Visiting Researcher - Dec 2018 - May 2019

Computer Vision and Speech Recognition

#### Research Fellow - School of AI - June 2019 till now

Few shot learning for myeloma detection - Ongoing

#### **Publications**

Gender classification techniques from Machine learning to Deep learning

International Journal of Control Theory and Applications

# **Projects**

#### Demographics Estimation using Deep Learning

Objective- Build demographics estimation model using Deep Learning Role

- Used transfer learning approach for predicting gender towards unfinished dissertation
- Used Matlab's Computer Vision toolbox
- Trained SVM on extracted features of AlexNet

Tools used - Matlab Computer Vision and Neural Network Toolbox

#### Damage Recognition Engine for Motor Insurance

Objective- Build a Damage Recognition Engine using semantic segmentation and object detection to estimate the claim amount for motor insurance

Role

- Formulated the problem, conducted literature review for relevant computer vision techniques
- Got the data labelled by Ops team with in-house tagging tool
- Trained object detection and semantic segmentation model with .65 MAP score on 100k images
- Model hyper parameter tuning by random search and grid search
- Deployed model with Tensorflow-serving in production

Tools used - Python, Tensorflow, Keras

### Speech Recognition for Trading - Cloud9

Objective: Build a Speech To Text model for trading for JP Morgan. This is called Cloud9, Cloud9 is Deep learning based ASR model trained on 4000 hours of trading speech data incorporates state of the art research papers in the domain of speech and language Role

- Implemented class based language model, language model interpolation

#### **Hierarchical Language Model Switching**

Objective: Predict most probable language model for given audio

- Build a CNN-LSTM architecture for dynamic language model switching while inference for Cloud9
- Provides dynamic LM selection out of 50 interpolated language models  $\,$

### Probabilistic Ride Allocation Modeling for Jugnoo Autos

Objective - Build a probabilistic model for continuous ride-acceptance probability assignment to Jugnoo drivers. Role

- Worked with sole ownership of project
- Extracted data from MySQL database, Data preprocessing, Feature engineering
- Model building, hyper-parameter tuning
- Designing REST endpoint for production use

Tools used- SQL, Bigquery, Python, Scikit-learn, Flask

# **Seminars & Achievements**

University Of San Francisco - International Fellowship, 2018
Presented paper in International Conference on Intelligent Circuits and Systems 2016
Attended workshop on Computational Social Systems, 2018
Computer Vision Summer School, IIIT-Allahabad, 2019

# **Blogs**

https://medium.com/@ranjeet\_thakur